<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Rebecca White's Blog</title>
		<link>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/</link>
		<description>Blog Updates</description>
		<language>en-gb</language>

		<item>
			<title>Ubuntu Is a Bad Distribution</title>
			<link>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2022/25_12_ubuntu_is_a_bad_distro</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 10:45:00 -0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2022/25_12_ubuntu_is_a_bad_distro</guid>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[
			<p>Ubuntu is seen as a "noob-friendly" distribution, and it does most of the "hard work"
			that is typically associated with better distributions; such as Arch or Gentoo. But
			while it does this work, it does a lot of other things. Badly.</p>

			<h2>Snap and Apt</h2>
			<p>Canonical, the company behind Ubuntu, has made their own "package manager" called Snap, and rather than making things easier, it makes everything much more annoying.
				While Canonical wants you to use Snap; Apt, the traditional Debian package management system, is still included. And to make things that bit more awkward - Apt and
				Snap are completely incompatibile with each other, and Snap packages take priority over Apt. Let's say you wanted to install Firefox on Ubuntu, you would do
				sudo apt-get install firefox, but no you wouldn't! Because that will install the Snap package instead. To install Firefox from apt, you would need to add the
				Mozilla Team's apt PPA (Personal Package Archive), remove Snap, and tell apt to prioritize the PPA over Snap Packages. There is no reason to do this. It is flawed.
			</p>
			
			<h2>Ubuntu's Painful Slowness</h2>
			<p>One of the things that I hate about Ubuntu is its painful slowness. Even with NVIDIA's proprietary driver. Unless you strip out Snap, it is unbearable slow. Let's say you wanted
				to play a game, let's say Valve's Half-Life 2 - a great game and highly recommend that you play it if you haven't done so, but just not on Ubuntu. Because if you try on
				Ubuntu, you will experience it in the worst possible way - Laggy and overall a bad experience. And consider this: Half-Life 2 isn't a game that has high system requirements.
				It is from 2004 - the Windows XP Era. However, on Arch Linux - it runs perfectly. Even in the GNOME Desktop Environment. Same hardware, and roughly the same software.
				You can view the system requirements on the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/220/HalfLife_2/">Half-Life 2 Steam Page</a>.
			</p>

			<h2>Why Use Ubuntu?</h2>
			<p>If Ubuntu is so bad... why do people use it? As mentioned, Ubuntu is seen as a "noob-friendly" distribution, and people who are new to using Linux, will typically go for Ubuntu,
				as it does everything for them. Ubuntu also has a server version, which is for use on... well, servers. And it doesn't include a GUI, but if you wanted a server distribution,
				you could use Debian, or even Arch.
			</p>

			<h2>Ubuntu Alternatives</h2>
			<p>If you are wanting a "just-works" distribution, but don't want Ubuntu, consider the following;</p>

			<h3>Arch Based</h3>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://artixlinux.org/">Artix Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://manjaro.org/">Manjaro Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://arcolinux.com/">Arco Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://endeavouros.com/">EndeavourOS</a></li>
			</ul>

			<h3>Debian Based</h3>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://debian.org">Debian GNU/Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://www.bunsenlabs.org/">Bunsenlabs Linux</a></li>
			</ul>
			]]>
			</description>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
