<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Rebecca White's Blog</title>
		<link>https://kimitzuni.github.io/articles/</link>
		<description>RSS Feed for the Blog</description>
		<language>en-gb</language>

		<item>
			<title>Ubuntu Is a Bad Distribution</title>
			<link>
				https://kimitzuni.github.io/articles/2022_12_25-ubuntu_is_a_bad_distro.html
			</link>

			<pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 10:45:00 -0000</pubDate>

			<description>
       <![CDATA[
			<p>Ubuntu is seen as a "noob-friendly" distribution, and it does most of the "hard work" that is typically associated with better
			   distributions; such as Arch or Gentoo. But while it does this work, it does a lot of other things. Badly.
                       </p>

		       <h2 id="snap-and-apt">Snap and Apt</h2>
		       <p>Canonical, the company behind Ubuntu, has made their own "package manager" called <b>Snap</b>, and rather than making things easier,
		          it makes everything much more annoying. While Canonical wants you to use Snap; Apt, the traditional Debian package management system,
			  is still included. And to make things that bit more awkward - Apt and Snap are completely incompatibile with each other, and Snap
			  packages take priority over Apt. Let's say you wanted to install Firefox on Ubuntu, you would do
			  <code>sudo apt-get install firefox</code>, but no you wouldn't! Because that will install the Snap package instead. To install Firefox
			  from apt, you would need to add the Mozilla Team's apt PPA (Personal Package Archive), remove Snap, and tell apt to prioritize the
			  PPA over Snap Packages. There is no reason to do this. It is flawed.</p>

			<p>Let's compare this to how you would install Firefox on Arch or Gentoo. On Arch you would do;
			   <code>sudo pacman -S firefox</code>, and on Gentoo - <code>sudo emerge firefox</code> (or <code>firefox-bin</code>). And then it's
			   installed. And that's it. Simple. This is how package management should be. Hence Arch Linux's phrase <i>Keep It Simple, Stupid</i>
			</p>

			<h2 id="ubuntus-painful-slowness">Ubuntu's Painful Slowness</h2>
			<p>One of the things that I hate about Ubuntu is its painful slowness. Even with NVIDIA's proprietary driver. Unless you strip out
			   Snap, it is unbearable slow. Let's say you wanted to play a game, let's say Valve's <i>Half-Life 2</i>, a very good game. You would
			   experience it in the worst way possible - laggy, and slow to run. Half-Life 2 isn't even a game that needs a lot of resources, it is
			   from 2007 after all. Now, let's compare it to Arch Linux, even with GNOME. It runs perfectly. Same hardware. <i>Roughly</i>, the same
			   software.</p>

			<h2 id="why-use-ubuntu">Why Use Ubuntu?</h2>
			<p>If Ubuntu is so bad... why do people use it? As mentioned, Ubuntu is seen as a "noob-friendly" distribution, and people who are new
			   to using Linux, will typically go for Ubuntu, as it does everything for them. Ubuntu also has a server version, which is for use on...
			   well, servers. And it doesn't include a GUI, but if you wanted a server distribution, you could use Debian, or even Arch.
			   </p>

			<h2 id="ubuntu-alternatives">Ubuntu Alternatives</h2>
			<p>If you are wanting a "just-works" distribution, but don't want Ubuntu, consider the following;</p>

			<h3 id="arch-based">Arch Based</h3>
			
			<div class="rec-left">
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://artixlinux.org/">Artix Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://manjaro.org/">Manjaro Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://arcolinux.com/">Arco Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://endeavouros.com/">EndeavourOS</a></li>
			</ul>
			</div>

			<h3 id="debian-based">Debian Based</h3>
			<div class="rec-right">
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://debian.org">Debian GNU/Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://www.bunsenlabs.org/">Bunsenlabs Linux</a></li>
			</ul>
			</div>]]></description>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
