<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Rebecca White's Blog</title>
		<link>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/</link>
		<description>Blog Updates</description>
		<language>en-gb</language>

		<item>
			<title>Maybe, Ubuntu Isn't That Bad</title>
			<link>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2023/07_01_maybe_ubuntus_not_that_bad</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 7 Jan 2023 18:17:00 -0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2023/07_01_maybe_ubuntus_not_that_bad</guid>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[

			<p>
			In a previous blog post, I complained about Canonical's <i>Ubuntu</i> distribution. However, I think that
			I got some things wrong in that post, and I want to correct some of those things. If you want to read the
			original blog post, you can do - <a href="https://kimitzuni.me/blog/2022/25_12_ubuntu_is_a_bad_distro">Ubuntu
			Is A Bad Distribution</a>.
			</p>

			<h2 id="ubuntus-flavours">Ubuntu's Flavours</h2>
			<p>In the previous blog post, I focused primarily on <b>Ubuntu</b>. Stock, vanilla plain Ubuntu that you
			can download from <a href="https://ubuntu.com">Ubuntu's Website</a>. GNOME 40. That version. However, there
			are other "flavours" of Ubuntu that have different desktop environments, such as Ubuntu with MATE -
			<a href="https://ubuntu-mate.org/">Ubuntu MATE</a>, or Ubuntu with KDE Plasma -
			<a href="https://kubuntu.org/">Kubuntu</a>. And I highly recommend the Kubuntu distribution, it's one of the
			nicest feeling versions of Ubuntu. I don't know how to explain it, but it feels very nice. But in this post,
			I will be focusing on <a href="https://ubuntuunity.org/">Ubuntu Unity</a>, which is the flavour of Ubuntu
			that uses the old Unity desktop environment from pre-18.04, and I just prefer this desktop over GNOME. So, I
			have this distribution installed on all my machines, except for the Ryzen Laptop, and I have been using it
			for a couple of weeks, and here's what I have to say about this over Ubuntu.
			<br><br>

			It feels much... faster, a lot more responsive, even with Snap packages. The slowness is, sometimes still there
			however it is a lot less prevalent.
			</p>

			<h2 id="steam-on-ubuntu">Steam on Ubuntu</h2>
			<p>Steam on Ubuntu is a lot better than Steam on openSUSE, as it works. I was completely wrong on the performance
			of games on Ubuntu, and specifically my take on running <i>Half-Life 2</i> on Ubuntu being unplayable. This was
			plain wrong. My aim is to not misinform people, and I use the blog as a place to express myself, and talk about
			things I find interesting, but this was outright wrong, and I'm sorry for that. Here is the actual performance of
			Half-Life 2 on Ubuntu: Exactly the same as on Windows. You can play it. It's not laggy at all. There is occasionally
			some lag, but mostly between loading zones, and even then I put that down to - It's loading stuff. Other games, such
			as <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/362890/Black_Mesa/">Black Mesa</a>, the Half-Life: Source remake,
			perform equally as well. There is some lagging with that, but it is a more graphics intensive game.</p>

			<h3 id="sou-issues">Issues</h3>
			<p>There are some issues with Steam on Ubuntu, and this mostly has to do with the suspend/sleep function of the
			distribution - Once leaving suspend, the UI of the Steam program just breaks. It's still usable, but broken. I
			have no idea why it does this, but other programs like Chrome also break in the same way.
			</p>

			<h2 id="recommended-ubuntu-distros">Recommended Ubuntu Distros</h2>
			<p>I do recommend some Ubuntu and Ubuntu based distributions, such as
			<a href="https://kubuntu.org">Kubuntu</a> and <a href="https://ubuntuunity.org">Ubuntu Unity</a>, however there is
			another called <a href="https://linuxmint.com/">Linux Mint</a>, which uses the Cinnamon Desktop Environment and
			provides a more Windows-esque experience.
			</p> ]]>
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>Make Better Output Logs</title>
			<link>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2022/30_12_make_better_output_logs</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 17:59:00 -0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2022/30_12_make_better_output_logs</guid>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[
			<p>The fact that most programs on Linux don't have an output log that actually tells you what goes wrong
			is very frustrating. It would help a lot of people to just have an extra bit of the output tell you what
				went wrong. This is also more of a rant about Steam on Linux, more than anything else.</p>


			<h2 id="valve-pls-fix">Valve, Pls Fix</h2>
			<p>My frustration of this was recently heightened by Valve, and mostly with Steam. While I am a software developer, I do like to play games, recently I've
			been playing through the Half-Life 2 series, and I'm currently on <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/420/HalfLife_2_Episode_Two/">HL2 - Episode 2</a>,
				and I wanted to continue that. So, I installed opened Steam... and nothing. I thought, lets try it through the terminal. So that's what I did</p>

			<pre>

~ $ steam
Couldn't import apt, please install python3-apt or update steamdeps for your distribution.
steam.sh[727]: Running Steam on opensuse-tumbleweed 20221229 64-bit
steam.sh[727]: STEAM_RUNTIME is enabled automatically
setup.sh[809]: Steam runtime environment up-to-date!
steam.sh[727]: Steam client's requirements are satisfied
			</pre>

			<p>
			And still nothing. No log file that told me what went wrong, and just by looking at this output, you'd think it worked, because it didn't have any obvious
			failures. But Steam still didn't open. So I now had to debug a program that should've been debugged by the multi-billion dollar comapny. So I ran <code>strace</code>
				on Steam.</p>

			<pre>

~ $ strace steam
execve("/usr/bin/steam", ["steam"], 0x7ffc209ad230 /* 91 vars */) = 0
brk(NULL)                               = 0x55d566470000
arch_prctl(0x3001 /* ARCH_??? */, 0x7fffbd8890f0) = -1 EINVAL (Invalid argument)
mmap(NULL, 8192, PROT_READ|PROT_WRITE, MAP_PRIVATE|MAP_ANONYMOUS, -1, 0) = 0x7f14fa062000
access("/etc/ld.so.preload", R_OK)      = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/glibc-hwcaps/x86-64-v3/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/glibc-hwcaps/x86-64-v3", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/glibc-hwcaps/x86-64-v2/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/glibc-hwcaps/x86-64-v2", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls/haswell/x86_64/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls/haswell/x86_64", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls/haswell/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls/haswell", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls/x86_64/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls/x86_64", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/tls", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/haswell/x86_64/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/haswell/x86_64", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/haswell/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/haswell", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/x86_64/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/x86_64", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash/libreadline.so.8", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
newfstatat(AT_FDCWD, "/usr/lib64/bash", 0x7fffbd888320, 0) = -1 ENOENT (No such file or directory)
openat(AT_FDCWD, "/etc/ld.so.cache", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = 3
newfstatat(3, "", {st_mode=S_IFREG|0644, st_size=78295, ...}, AT_EMPTY_PATH) = 0
mmap(NULL, 78295, PROT_READ, MAP_PRIVATE, 3, 0) = 0x7f14fa04e000
close(3)

			</pre>
			<br>
			
			And oh dear. That's quite a lot of libraries that just aren't found. Bare in mind that I had managed to open Steam previously, to install the games. But after a 
			restart... It broke. Without telling me why or how. I decided to delete all trace of Steam from my home directory, and reinstall Steam. Steam did start working,
			and on multiple closing and reopenings of it. But this was before I logged in. Though during its update thing, I did load Steam from the <code>$HOME/.steam</code>
			binary, and that decided it would crash.

			<br>
				<pre>

(steam:6469): GLib-GObject-CRITICAL **: 15:00:25.179: g_object_unref: assertion 'G_IS_OBJECT (object)' failed
crash_20221230150025_25.dmp[6954]: Uploading dump (out-of-process)
/tmp/dumps/crash_20221230150025_25.dmp
/home/rtiannew/.local/share/Steam/steam.sh: line 798:  6469 Segmentation fault      (core dumped) "$STEAMROOT/$STEAMEXEPATH" "$@"
~ $ crash_20221230150025_25.dmp[6954]: Finished uploading minidump (out-of-process): success = yes
crash_20221230150025_25.dmp[6954]: response: CrashID=bp-526424d3-c755-4318-b5a3-413942221230
crash_20221230150025_25.dmp[6954]: file ''/tmp/dumps/crash_20221230150025_25.dmp'', upload yes: ''CrashID=bp-526424d3-c755-4318-b5a3-413942221230''

			</pre>
			<br>

	I just thought that was kind of funny. But the library did infact load (<a href="https://kimitzuni.github.io/assets/blogimg/2022_30_12_better_output_logs_steamlibrary.png">View Image</a>)</p>

	<p>So I downloaded Half-Life 2 - Episode 2 and it loaded. This is good progress. (<a href="https://kimitzuni.github.io/blogimg/2022_30_12_better_output_logs_hl2e2.png">View Image</a>)</p>

	<p>But will Steam still load when I restart it? There's only one way to find out. (Side note - I'm also doing this <i>as</i> I write this.) And it did indeed load. However,
		there is still one more test. Will it load after a full restart? And the answer is... Actually yes
	(<a href="https://kimitzuni.github.io/assets/blogimg/2022_30_12_better_output_logs_post_restart.png">View Image</a></p>

		<h3 id="a-note-about-steamcmd">A Note about <i>steamcmd</i></h3>
			<p>One thing that I do like is a command line only version of programs, and Steam does have this with <i>steamcmd</i>, though that was just out of the question.
				It didn't even work. At all.
			<br>
				<pre>

~ $ steamcmd
.......
[ 97%] Downloading update (56,907 of 57,385 KB)...
[ 99%] Downloading update (57,385 of 57,385 KB)...
[100%] Download Complete.
[100%] !!! Fatal Error: Download of package (steamcmd_public_all) failed after 0 bytes (0).

			</pre><br></p>

			<h2 id="suggestions">Suggestions</h2>
			<p>If you want to make the users of your programs avoid headaches like this, and make it so they don't have to use <code>strace</code> to figure out what is going
			on and why the program just won't work. Add a <code>--debug</code> type flag to your program, that gives just that little bit of extra information. And if you 
				really want to help your users. Make a log file somewhere common.</p>
				]]>
		</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>Ubuntu Is a Bad Distribution</title>
			<link>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2022/25_12_ubuntu_is_a_bad_distro</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 10:45:00 -0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://kimitzuni.github.io/blog/2022/25_12_ubuntu_is_a_bad_distro</guid>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[
			<p>Ubuntu is seen as a "noob-friendly" distribution, and it does most of the "hard work"
			that is typically associated with better distributions; such as Arch or Gentoo. But
			while it does this work, it does a lot of other things. Badly.</p>

			<h2>Snap and Apt</h2>
			<p>Canonical, the company behind Ubuntu, has made their own "package manager" called Snap, and rather than making things easier, it makes everything much more annoying.
				While Canonical wants you to use Snap; Apt, the traditional Debian package management system, is still included. And to make things that bit more awkward - Apt and
				Snap are completely incompatibile with each other, and Snap packages take priority over Apt. Let's say you wanted to install Firefox on Ubuntu, you would do
				sudo apt-get install firefox, but no you wouldn't! Because that will install the Snap package instead. To install Firefox from apt, you would need to add the
				Mozilla Team's apt PPA (Personal Package Archive), remove Snap, and tell apt to prioritize the PPA over Snap Packages. There is no reason to do this. It is flawed.
			</p>
			
			<h2>Ubuntu's Painful Slowness</h2>
			<p>One of the things that I hate about Ubuntu is its painful slowness. Even with NVIDIA's proprietary driver. Unless you strip out Snap, it is unbearable slow. Let's say you wanted
				to play a game, let's say Valve's Half-Life 2 - a great game and highly recommend that you play it if you haven't done so, but just not on Ubuntu. Because if you try on
				Ubuntu, you will experience it in the worst possible way - Laggy and overall a bad experience. And consider this: Half-Life 2 isn't a game that has high system requirements.
				It is from 2004 - the Windows XP Era. However, on Arch Linux - it runs perfectly. Even in the GNOME Desktop Environment. Same hardware, and roughly the same software.
				You can view the system requirements on the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/220/HalfLife_2/">Half-Life 2 Steam Page</a>.
			</p>

			<h2>Why Use Ubuntu?</h2>
			<p>If Ubuntu is so bad... why do people use it? As mentioned, Ubuntu is seen as a "noob-friendly" distribution, and people who are new to using Linux, will typically go for Ubuntu,
				as it does everything for them. Ubuntu also has a server version, which is for use on... well, servers. And it doesn't include a GUI, but if you wanted a server distribution,
				you could use Debian, or even Arch.
			</p>

			<h2>Ubuntu Alternatives</h2>
			<p>If you are wanting a "just-works" distribution, but don't want Ubuntu, consider the following;</p>

			<h3>Arch Based</h3>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://artixlinux.org/">Artix Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://manjaro.org/">Manjaro Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://arcolinux.com/">Arco Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://endeavouros.com/">EndeavourOS</a></li>
			</ul>

			<h3>Debian Based</h3>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://debian.org">Debian GNU/Linux</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://www.bunsenlabs.org/">Bunsenlabs Linux</a></li>
			</ul>
			]]>
			</description>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
